Plotkin, Abraham Collection 6036/016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Abraham Plotkin Collection
1911-1978
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Plotkin, Abraham
6036/016
2.5 cubic feet
2.5 linear ft.
Records, correspondence.
This collection documents Plotkin's work as an ILGWU organizer in the Midwest, Florida, Hawaii, and on the Pacific Coast. It also contains correspondence with European trade unionists, and Plotkin's diary on his time in Germany in 1932-1933 and his experiences in Berlin during the Nazi rise to power. Includes trip to International Clothing Workers Federation Congress in Vienna. Also articles in manuscript on various aspects of life in Berlin.
5767586
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 05, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Abraham Plotkin was born on August 22, 1892 (1893) in the Ukraine. After arriving with his family in the United States, they initially lived in Philadelphia before settling in New York. Plotkin soon had to work to supplement the family income and became employed in a small sweatshop. He continued to hold odd jobs while working on his education; attending night classes in New York City and taking courses at a Denver law school, though he did not obtain his degree. Plotkin was interested and became involved in Socialism, labor, and union organizing. As a young adult, he joined the International Ladies Garment Workers Union and remained a prominent figure in the organization for most of his adulthood. He died in May of 1988, at age 96.
Scope and Contents
The collection has three distinct components. The first section of the collection mainly consists of correspondence, collected articles and clippings organized alphabetically by either individual or subject. There is letters, expenses and documents about or during his travels, across the country while he was a representative of the ILGWU on the Pacific Coast, and abroad when he toured several countries in Europe visiting Socialist and labor institutions. Some of the other subjects include correspondence with Joseph Breslow, Jean Bangs (first wife), Maurice Brown, Max Danish, including copies of articles Danish had written as well as stories and poems, David Dubinsky, Melech Epstein and Diego Rivera. Available is photographs, programs, clippings and articles from the AFL Conference to Combat Intolerance held in Chicago in 1949. Information is also included on the strike of the H.W. Gossard Co. in 1941 along with clippings and a copy of the agreement with the union. The remainder of the correspondence in this section of the collection documents Plotkin's role as an ILGWU representative and organizer. Notable are the files from his time as the ILGWU representative in Hawaii which contains information and letters documenting the garment industry, factories, and homework situation as well as the standard of living for garment workers on the island. Also significant are the correspondence, reports, recommendations and clippings documenting Plotkin's involvement helping to organize Miami shops through meetings, leaflets and articles. Photographs throughout the collection have been digitized and include portraits of Plotkin, group shots of locals, meetings and conferences, staff and board members, strikes, and his travels such as Florida and his time in Berlin.
The second component of the collection consists of National Labor Relations Board Hearings including the Carson Pirie Scott & Company, the Decatur Garment Company, and the A.F. Keating Company all in Chicago, as well as Wage Board Recommendations and minimum fair wage standards for garment industries in Illinois.
The remainder of the collection is composed of the typed manuscript of Plotkin's time in Berlin in 1932-1933. He begins in October 25, 1932. His diary recounts his travels, individuals he met
As well as his published article "Destruction of the Labor Movement in Germany"
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Arrangement
Series I. ILGWU
Series II. Germany
Series III. Journal Posts
Plotkin, Abraham, -- 1893-1988.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5767586
- Series I. ILGWU
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, reports on Union activities in Mid-West, Miami, Florida, Pacific Coast and Hawaii. Correspondence with European trade unionists during 1930s on European political and economic situation.
  - A, 1933-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advance, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Volume 6, Number 49: February 2.
  - Agreements, notes on negotiations, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Federation of Labor, Conference to Combat Intolerance, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B, 1931-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes: Joseph Breslaw letters and letters to Jean Bangs (first wife) relating experiences of his Pacific Coast travels, 1931.
  - Chicago, 1946-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - D, 1933-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Danish, Max, 1911-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Articles (short stories), poems, manuscripts.
  - Dubinsky, David, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Epstein, Melech, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - F, 1930-1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - G, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Germany (and East Europe), 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Correspondence
  - H, 1923-1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - H.W. Gossard Company, Logansport, Indiana, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Agreement
  - Hartig, Valtin, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Correspondence on European situation
  - Hawaii, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Correspondence and reports on all facets of Union activity; agreements.
  - Hawaii, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Newspaper clipping files
  - Hege, Bob, 1961-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - I, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Impartial arbitration decision between garment industries in Illinois and Union
  - J, 1932-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Letters from William Jaffee and Raymond Johnson
  - K, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Fritz Kummer letters on European (Germany) situation
  - Lieberman, Elias, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Los Angeles, California, 1931-1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Los Angeles, California, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - M, 1932-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miami, Florida, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes correspondence with David Dubinsky, all facets of Union activities
  - Miami, Florida, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miami, Florida, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - N, 1935-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Urban League, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondence and reports (notes on meeting of Picket Investiation Committee) on controversy between Urban League and Union
  - O-P, 1923-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Plettl, Martin and Dorothea, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Plettl, Martin and Dorothea, 1936-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Q-R, 1935-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rivera, Diego, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rufer, Harry, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - S, 1935-1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stolz, G.; Schevenels, W., 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Letters on European (Germany) situation
  - Stulberg, Louis, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondence on potential organizational work for Plotkin on Pacific Coast
  - T-U, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Van Der Heeg, T., 1933-1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Voorhis School for Boys, 1931-1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - W, 1952-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper clipping files (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Labor Relations Board Hearings [folder 1 of 3], 1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes: Carson Pirie Scott and Company, Chicago, Illinois; Decatur Garment Company, Chicago, Illinois; A.F. Keating Company, Chicago, Illinois.
  - National Labor Relations Board Hearings [folder 2 of 3], 1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Labor Relations Board Hearings [folder 3 of 3], 1935 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reports on Recommendations of the Wage Board for the Wash Dress Industry of Illinois for Minimum Fair Wage Standards, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Transcript of proceedings to make mandataory the directory order establishing minimum fair wage standards in the cotton garment industry in Illinois, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    June
- Series II. Germany
  Diary of Abraham Plotkin's trip to Germany in 1932-1933 and his experiences in Berlin during the Nazi rise to power. Includes trip to International Clothing Workers Federation Congress in Vienna. Also articles in manuscript on various aspects of life in Berlin.
  - Trip to Berlin, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Manuscript
  - "Berlin Lowdown", 1932 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Manuscript account of Abraham Plotkin's stay in Berlin and other articles; includes letters to Richard Rohman re publication
  - "Destruction of the Labor Movement in Germany", 1933 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Article from American Federationist, August 1933
  - Diary of Berlin Experiences, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Diary of Berlin Experiences, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Diary of Berlin Experiences, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Duplicate pages from diary (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Journal posts - Oct.25, 1932-Nov.1, 1932 (2 copies) (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series III. Journal Posts
  - Journal posts - Nov. 22, 1932-Nov.29, 1932 (some duplication) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Journal Posts - Nov. 24, 1932-Nov. 29, 1932 (some duplication) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Journal Posts - Dec.3, 1932-Dec.18, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Journal Posts - Jan.5, 1933-Feb.8, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 6)